Danielle Abrams Papers MS279
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Danielle Abrams Papers
circa 1950 -- 2022
circa 1993 -- 2022
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Abrams, Danielle
MS279
22 Linear Feet 14 record cartons and 2 oversized boxes
Contains the papers of Tufts professor and performance artist Danielle Abrams, including audio and video recordings, photographs, idea notebooks, and other records related to her artwork and career.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains subject files, notebooks, audiovisual media, photographs, slides, correspondence, catalogs, clippings, digital media including 1 Mac computer, realia, puppets, and other materials documenting Danielle Abram's artistic career.
Arrangement
Materials are organized in received order.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephanie Abrams, June 2022, accession MS-2023-008.
Biographical / Historical
Danielle Abrams (1968-2022) was a performance artist and a professor of the practice at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts at Tufts from 2014-2022.
Danielle Abrams was born in Queens, NY, on March 30, 1968, to Stephanie Belkin Abrams, a teacher and guidance counselor, and Eddie Abrams, a post office driver and furniture mover. After graduating from John Bowne High School in Flushing, she received a B.F.A. in painting and art education from Queens College (1992) and an M.F.A. in performance, video, and installation from the University of California at Irvine (1998). She held artists' residencies at the Yale School of Painting (1990) and the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture (1992).
In addition to teaching high school in New York City and San Francisco, Abrams taught at the City University of New York, St. Francis College in Brooklyn, the University of Michigan, and Goddard College. She first came to the School of the Museum of Fine Arts (SMFA) at Tufts as a visiting artist in 2014, and later became a professor of the practice in performance. Her family's African-American and Jewish heritage, and her identity as a mixed race queer woman, informed much of her work, as did historical research.
She was a Faculty Fellow at the Tisch College of Civic Life and a Visiting Scholar at the Midlo Center for New Orleans Studies at the University of New Orleans. In 2018, she was presented with the Distinguished Artist Award from the St. Botolph Club Foundation. Abrams died in Boston, MA, on April 21, 2022.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection may be limited depending on availability of appropriate playback equipment. Please contact the archives for details
Teaching and learning; Greater Boston arts; Performance art--United States--Boston, Mass.
- Subject files, circa 1990 -- 2020; MS279.000001 (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  This box may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
- Subject files, circa 1990 -- 2020; MS279.000002 (Box 2)
  Open for research.
- Files, source materials, and business cards, circa 1960 -- 2022; MS279.000003 (Box 3)
- Notebooks, circa 1990s -- 2022; MS279.000004 (Box 4)
- Notebooks, circa 1990s -- 2022; MS279.000005 (Box 5)
- Notebooks, circa 1990s -- 2022; MS279.000006 (Box 6)
- Photographs, circa 1950s -- 2020; MS279.000007 (Box 7)
- Photographs and publicity photos, circa 1975 -- 2010s; MS279.000008 (Box 8)
  Content Warning
  This box contains images of blackface, located in the folder entitled,"Postcards, images, word cards, circa 1980s-2020s." For more information on DCA's content warning policy please visit our website: website.
- Photographs and correspondence, circa 1960s -- 2010s; MS279.000009 (Box 9)
- Publicity and catalogs, 1994 -- 2018; MS279.000010 (Box 10)
- Slides, circa 1990s -- 2000s; MS279.000011 (Box 11)
- VHS tapes, 1991 -- 2005; MS279.000012 (Box 12)
- Mini-DVs and audiocassettes, 1991 -- 2009; MS279.000013 (Box 13)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Access to these materials may be limited depending on availability of appropriate playback equipment. Please contact the archives for details.
- Super 8 films and Umatic videotapes, circa 1970s -- 1990s; MS279.000014 (Box 14)
  This box contains a pornographic Super 8 film. For more information on DCA's content warning policy please visit our website.
- External drives, circa 2000s -- 2022; MS279.000015 (Box 15)
  These items may require review before they are available for use. Please contact DCA for more information.
- Puppets, circa 1990s -- 2022; MS279.000016 (Box 16)
- Mac computer, circa 2010 -- 2022; MS279.000017 (Object 17)
  This item may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for more information.